Growing up in Taiwan
خلال نشأتي في تايوان
as the daughter of a calligrapher,
كإبنة خطاط
one of my most treasured memories
كان من بين الذكريات العزيزة على قلبي
was my mother showing me the beauty, the shape
عندما كانت والدتي تريني جمال وشكل
and the form of Chinese characters.
وتكوين الحروف الصينية.
Ever since then, I was fascinated
ومنذ ذلك الحين، أصبحت مفتونة
by this incredible language.
بهذه اللغة الرائعة.
But to an outsider, it seems to be
ولكن للشخص الغريب، تبدو هذه اللغة
as impenetrable as the Great Wall of China.
صعبة الاختراق مثل سور الصين العظيم.
Over the past few years, I've been wondering
وعلى مدى السنوات القليلة الماضية، كنت أتسائل
if I can break down this wall,
إذا كان بإمكاني هدم هذا العائق،
so anyone who wants to understand and appreciate
حتى يتمكن أي شخص يرغب في فهم وتقدير
the beauty of this sophisticated language could do so.
جمال هذه اللغة الراقية من القيام بذلك.
I started thinking about how a new, fast method
بدأت أفكر في الكيفية التي يمكن من خلالها لطريقة جديدة وسريعة
of learning Chinese might be useful.
أن تفيد في تعليم اللغة الصينية.
Since the age of five, I started to learn how to draw
ومنذ كنت في سن الخامسة، بدأت أتعلم كيف أرسم
every single stroke for each character
كل خط من كل حرف
in the correct sequence.
بالترتيب الصحيح.
I learned new characters every day
وقد تعلمت حروفًا جديدة كل يوم
during the course of the next 15 years.
على مدار الخمسة عشر عامًا التالية.
Since we only have five minutes,
ولأنه لدينا خمس دقائق فقط،
it's better that we have a fast and simpler way.
فمن الأفضل أن يكون لدينا طريقة أسرع وأبسط.
A Chinese scholar would understand 20,000 characters.
يلزم على دارس اللغة الصينية أن يفهم 20000 حرفًا.
You only need 1,000 to understand the basic literacy.
ولكنكم تحتاجون إلى 1000 فقط لفهم المعارف الأساسية.
The top 200 will allow you to comprehend
سيمكّنكم أول 200 حرفًا من فهم
40 percent of basic literature --
40 بالمائة من الآداب الأساسية للغة
enough to read road signs, restaurant menus,
وهو ما يكفي لقراءة إشارات الطرق وقوائم المطاعم
to understand the basic idea of the web pages
وفهم الأفكار الأساسية لصفحات الإنترنت
or the newspapers.
أو الجرائد.
Today I'm going to start with eight
واليوم سأبدأ بثمانية حروف فقط
to show you how the method works.
لأريكم كيف تعمل هذه الطريقة.
You are ready?
هل أنتم مستعدون؟
Open your mouth as wide as possible
افتحوا أفواهكم بأوسع ما يمكنكم
until it's square.
حتى تصبح على شكل مربع.
You get a mouth.
وبذلك تحصلون على فم.
This is a person going for a walk.
هذا شخص ذاهب للتنزه.
Person.
شخص.
If the shape of the fire is a person
إذا كان شكل النار يبدو كامرأة
with two arms on both sides,
لها ذراعان بكلا الجانبين،
as if she was yelling frantically,
كما لو أنها تصرخ باهتياج قائلة،
"Help! I'm on fire!" --
"النجدة! أنا أحترق!"
This symbol actually is originally from the shape of the flame,
يعود أصل هذا الرمز في الواقع إلى شكل اللهب،
but I like to think that way. Whichever works for you.
ولكنني أحب التفكير فيه بتلك الطريقة، يمكنكم اختيار ما يناسبكم.
This is a tree.
هذه شجرة.
Tree.
شجرة.
This is a mountain.
هذا جبل.
The sun.
الشمس.
The moon.
القمر.
The symbol of the door
رمز الباب
looks like a pair of saloon doors in the wild west.
يبدو مثل زوج من أبواب الحانات في الغرب الأمريكي.
I call these eight characters radicals.
أطلق على هذه الحروف الثمانية اسم "الجذور".
They are the building blocks
فهي تمثل العناصر الأساسية التي ستساعدكم
for you to create lots more characters.
لتتمكنوا من ابتكار العديد من الحروف الأخرى.
A person.
الشخص.
If someone walks behind, that is "to follow."
إذا كان هناك رمز لشخص يسير بالخلف، فذلك يعني "أن تتبع".
As the old saying goes,
وكما يقول المثل القديم،
two is company, three is a crowd.
شخصان يمثلان صحبة، أما ثلاثة فزحام.
If a person stretched their arms wide,
وإذا كان هناك رمز لشخص يفتح ذراعيه على اتساعهما،
this person is saying, "It was this big."
فهذا الشخص يقول، "لقد كان بهذا الحجم."
The person inside the mouth, the person is trapped.
رمز الشخص داخل الفم يشير إلى شخص محبوس.
He's a prisoner, just like Jonah inside the whale.
إنه سجين، مثل يونس داخل الحوت.
One tree is a tree. Two trees together, we have the woods.
شجرة واحدة تعني شجرة. شجرتان معًا، ترمزان إلى أجمة.
Three trees together, we create the forest.
أما عند جمع ثلاث أشجار معًا، تصبح لدينا غابة.
Put a plank underneath the tree, we have the foundation.
ضعوا لوحًا خشبيًا أسفل الشجرة، يصبح لدينا رمز "الأساس".
Put a mouth on the top of the tree, that's "idiot." (Laughter)
ضعوا فمًا فوق الشجرة، هذا رمز "الحمق." (ضحك)
Easy to remember,
يسهل تذكره،
since a talking tree is pretty idiotic.
لأن الشجرة المتكلمة هو أمر في غاية الحمق.
Remember fire?
هل تتذكرون النار؟
Two fires together, I get really hot.
عندما نضع رمزان للنار معًا، فهذا يعني "أشعر حقًا بالحرارة".
Three fires together, that's a lot of flames.
ثلاث نيران معًا، يرمز ذلك إلى الكثير من ألسنة اللهب.
Set the fire underneath the two trees, it's burning.
أشعلوا النار أسفل الشجرتين، يصبح لدينا رمز "الاحتراق".
For us, the sun is the source of prosperity.
بالنسبة لنا، الشمس هي مصدر الازدهار.
Two suns together, prosperous.
رمز شمسان معًا، يعني "مزدهر".
Three together, that's sparkles.
ثلاث شموس معًا، هذا "التألق".
Put the sun and the moon shining together,
ضعوا رمزا الشمس والقمر وهما يسطعان معًا،
it's brightness.
هذا رمز "البريق".
It also means tomorrow, after a day and a night.
كما يعني أيضًا "غدًا" و"بعد يوم" و"ليلة".
The sun is coming up above the horizon. Sunrise.
الشمس تظهر فوق الأفق. إنه شروق الشمس.
A door. Put a plank inside the door,
الباب. ضعوا لوحًا داخل الباب،
it's a door bolt.
يصبح لدينا رمز "مزلاج الباب".
Put a mouth inside the door, asking questions.
ضعوا فمًا داخل الباب، هذا معناه توجيه أسئلة.
Knock knock. Is anyone home?
دق دق، هل هناك أحد بالمنزل؟
This person is sneaking out of a door,
هذا الشخص يتسلل عبر الباب، مما يعني
escaping, evading.
فرار، تهرب
On the left, we have a woman.
على اليسار، لدينا امرأة.
Two women together, they have an argument.
إمرأتان معًا، يعني أنهما تتشاجران.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Three women together, be careful, it's adultery.
ثلاث نساء معًا، انتبهوا، إنها مغازلة.
So we have gone through almost 30 characters.
إذًا، لقد استعرضنا 30 حرفًا تقريبًا.
By using this method, the first eight radicals
من خلال استخدام هذه الطريقة، ستمكنكم الجذور الثمانية الأولى
will allow you to build 32.
من بناء 32 حرفًا.
The next group of eight characters
وستساعدكم مجموعة الحروف الثمانية التالية
will build an extra 32.
على بناء 32 حرفًا إضافيًا.
So with very little effort,
وبذلك، ومع قليل من الجهد
you will be able to learn a couple hundred characters,
ستتمكنون من تعلم بضع مئات من الحروف،
which is the same as a Chinese eight-year-old.
مثل طفل صيني عمره ثمانية أعوام.
So after we know the characters, we start building phrases.
وهكذا، بعد أن نتعلم الحروف، نبدأ في بناء العبارات.
For example, the mountain and the fire together,
فمثلًا، عند جمع الجبل والنار معًا،
we have fire mountain. It's a volcano.
يصبح لدينا جبل نار، أي بركان.
We know Japan is the land of the rising sun.
نحن نعلم أن اليابان هي أرض الشمس المشرقة.
This is a sun placed with the origin,
هذا رمز الشمس موضوع بجانب رمز الأساس،
because Japan lies to the east of China.
ولأن اليابان تقع إلى الشرق من الصين
So a sun, origin together, we build Japan.
لذلك، فبوضع رمز الشمس والأساس معًا، نكوّن كلمة "اليابان".
A person behind Japan, what do we get?
وعند وضع رمز الشخص وراء اليابان، على ماذا نحصل؟
A Japanese person.
شخص ياباني.
The character on the left is two mountains
الحرف الموجود على اليسار يوضح جبلين
stacked on top of each other.
موضوعين فوق بعضهما.
In ancient China, that means in exile,
في الصين القديمة، كان ذلك يعني "في المنفى"،
because Chinese emperors, they put their political enemies
لأن الأباطرة الصينيين كانوا يضعون أعدائهم السياسيين
in exile beyond mountains.
في المنفى وراء الجبال.
Nowadays, exile has turned into getting out.
وفي أيامنا الحالية، تحولت كلمة المنفى إلى الخروج.
A mouth which tells you where to get out
رمز الفم الذي يخبرك عن مكان الخروج
is an exit.
يعني "مخرج".
This is a slide to remind me that I should stop talking
وهذه الشريحة لتذكيري بأنه عليّ أن أتوقف عن الحديث
and get off of the stage. Thank you.
وأغادر المسرح. شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
تصفيق